Welcome back and today we are going to
cover the part three of distributed
logging. So if you have not seen part
one and part two I would highly
recommend kindly go to it because in the
part one we have covered like its
low-level design, highle design of the
logging framework uh level inheritance,
parent child hierarchy
and in part two we have discussed about
appenders in depth like console file
rolling and different policies time size
plus time everything.
Now very important parts we are going to
cover in this uh part three is like a
sync
async logging and then another important
is structured logging
okay yes this is a very huge topic and
very important so we are I'm trying my
best we do not skip any subtopics okay
so let's start without wasting any time
the syning part so till now whatever we
have done All everything logging is
doing happens in the sync nature. So
whatever the appenders write to the file
whether to DB to Kafka
to file all the logging happens in the
sync nature means your request
thread waits for the logging work to
finish.
And this is very critical because in a
heavy traffic when you have so many
traffic so many logs statement to write
means so many log statement means you
might have to do so many uh operations
on DB or Kafka or file it could impact
your latency and thus overall impact on
the performance of the application
that's where the sync logging
feature comes into the picture.
So a sync is generally of two type as
sync appender and a sync logger. So
let's see appender first. So in this
async appender which is a log back
feature only appender work is a sync. So
now let's say that when our request when
our request thread
does log.info
after this lot of other small task
happen like this this statement is
converted to let's say log event. After
that level checking is happen. So there
are another sub operations which might
be happening. So that again all happen
in sync.
But only this part the formatting and
writing to appender like writing via
appender that only happens through
async.
So in the async appender only a specific
task
and the task is the log formatting and
the appender like where we write the log
statement to an output that is only done
through a different thread and in a sync
nature. Other subtask like level check
or creation of log events from this
log.info info all everything happen in
sync
but in a sync logger which is log 4j2
feature complete logging pipeline is a
sync means once you did this log.info
info after that everything is happen a
sync. Okay. So this is good for highle
traffic where you want very minimal
latency for the logging. This is good
for medium level traffic. So here we are
good uh but latency might be little bit
higher than this a sync logger
also. Logback generally do not support a
sync logger only. Okay. Here we have
only a sing appender. In the logback
framework we have only a sing appender.
We don't have a sing logger. Whereas if
you're using log 4j2 you have both. You
have a sing appender and you have a sing
logger too. But at least you know the
difference that in as appender only this
formatting and append appender work is a
async rest other happens in still in
sync. In async logger everything after
you done log.info info or log. error or
log.1 everything happen in async.
So since we are doing log back framework
so I would be covering a sing appender.
Okay. And yes this is a pretty much used
because this is for good for medium
level traffic and this works for most of
the majority of the cases.
So in async appender what happens is
that let's say your request comes you
did log.info info and after that there's
something task like level check log
events done. As soon as that is done, so
we put the event log event to a que and
as soon as the log event is put to the
queue, your request thread become free.
And now this Q holds log events and then
we have a worker thread which take out
this log event from the Q and pass it to
the appender and appender write it to
the log statement. So from the above
diagram couple of things we need to
notice that a sync appender is just a
wrapper actual work is still done by
appender only. So this is the one which
actually does all the work of writing.
Okay only thing is we are just providing
a wrapper above it that okay instead of
directly
sending the request or log event to
appender we are first accepting into the
queue. From the queue a worker thread
pick the task and pass it to appender.
Okay. So async appender provide Q
facility and also provide worker thread
facility which pick the event from the
queue and pass it to appender. So this
is how we write an async appender. So
this is nothing but a normal file
appender
which we have already seen in the part
two like how to create appender. So this
is nothing but a file appender. Now I am
creating one appender. Okay. Okay. And I
have given it a name a sync file. Okay.
You can give any name. And the class
which I'm using it a sync appender. So
here I am creating now a sync appender.
I told you it's just a wrapper. Okay. So
this a sync appender which I'm writing
it might pass a request to one specific
appender. Right? So here reference
appending reference to which appender.
So here it is referencing to this file.
Okay. Now it also provide Q and worker
thread capacity. So we can decide what
is the Q size. Capacity by default is
256. If you don't write it but if you
want to change it you can like Q size
1,000 if you want it. Okay. Then we have
something called worker thread. Worker
thread by default it has only one worker
thread. Okay. And generally uh there is
no configuration that to increase the
worker thread. It only has one worker
thread which works on the queue
and then there is something called
discarding threshold. So discarding
threshold like you can give any value
like 10 20 50. So what does it mean when
you give 10 what does it mean that? So
till Q whatever the Q we have let's say
that it size is 0 to 99 100.
So till the Q size doesn't reach 90 it
will accept all kind of log events debug
trace info error want all are accepted
but as soon as the size reach till 90
and only 10% space is left. So for this
10%
only critical events will be accepted.
Generally error, warn and info these are
generally considered as you can say that
critical debug and trace would be
rejected. Okay. So last 10% would be
kept only for critical uh non-critical
would be discarded. Okay. So if you have
like 40 so till 60%
everything would be accepted in the
queue and for last 40% of the queue only
critical info error one would be
accepted by the queue the rest is not
accepted this uh like your debug trace
okay and there is also one more thing
like never block true false so we can
write it like here never block true
false what does it mean now let's say
when the Q is full.
When the queue is full and your request
is trying to insert an event, does it
has to wait or not? So by default is
false. Okay. So means the request thread
blocks if the que is full. If the que is
full, it wait for the space in the
queue. But if you make it true,
it request thread drop the log itself.
But request thread do not wait. If there
is no space, the log would be dropped
and the request thread would get free
immediately. It won't wait for the space
to get uh created within a queue.
Okay. So these are the
configuration you can use in an async
appender. So name anything you can give
the class async appender the actual
appender which this async has to call
the Q size and like discarding threshold
and never block. Okay. And here if you
see this is our logger. Okay. Level is
info. Additivity is false. We have
already seen the appender which it we
are associating it this a sync one.
Now one important thing to consider is
that what happen in case of app shutdown
because the queue which is created is in
memory.
So when the JVM stops let's say your JVM
you shut down the app. So when you shut
down the app JVM does not shut down
instantly. It performs certain cleanups.
So during that time what happens to the
async appender is first it will stop
accepting any new log event. It will not
accept any new log event even if there
is a space and it try to flush the event
as soon as possible but it does not
guarantee because as soon as JVM
shutdown this queue is discarded. So any
event present into the queue will get
discarded.
So there is always a risk of losing the
events in case of a sync appender or you
can say that in case of a sync logging
itself.
So my recommendation is that for warn
info debug trace we can go for a sync
but for critical error is something
which I would say that it is critical
because if any customer issue comes say
this is not working then this error log
is something which can help us. So this
I consider is a very critical event. So
for that only we can go for sync but for
all others we can go for a sing. Why?
Because uh even though we can for error
also we can go for a singing and we can
make that okay never block true or uh
never block false means if the Q is full
wait don't just discard the Q. But we
can also have like okay only for warning
info debug trace we can go for a sync
for error I will go for sync that also
we can do just to make sure that Q size
full or application restart in scenario
in those cases my critical event does
not lost.
So I will just give you an example that
how we can do that. Uh we can make use
of filter. We also have filters in
appender. we can make use of it. So just
see this example. So what I am trying to
here show you that we have a sync
appender.
A sync appender writes to a file.
Uh this file name is noncritical.
So here info
warn debug trace
will go. Then we have uh one more file
critical
here error log will go only error log
only okay and all this info debug on
this file it will happen in async and
this will happen in sync
so we want this functionality how we can
do that so here if you see that
I am uh I have created one let's say
first appender is non-critical
Okay. So, appender name is file not
critical. I am using a file appender for
example. And the file name which it will
create is non-critical app.log. This
file non-critical app.log. This is the
file it will create. And I have now
created one a sync appender which is a
wrapper above it. So the name you can
give anything. I give a sync. The class
is a sync appender. Okay. and uh the
appender which is which I'm associating
it with like file not critical one this
append this one so it's just an appender
above this file appender which will
create this non-critical file
now here if you see that I am writing
one filter
okay so we can also have filter within
appender
so we can have different filter like
level filter okay and we have another
like threshold filter So these are all
present within the logback framework
itself. There are more but these two are
popular. You can check out the
documentation. We have more filters but
these are very frequently used. Level
filter and threshold filter. So in level
filter what generally happen is a
particular
level we can decide what to do. For
example here what is our
expectation here in this one. So when
any request comes here, so here it will
come all it will come info it will come
want it will come error uh debug trace
everything request will come try to put
into the queue okay but I want to put a
filter hey before putting into the Q
only remove error one rest all I can
take because ultimately I want to put
into non-critical which accept all
except error Okay. So that's what I'm
doing. Filter level filter I'm using
because I need to work on one particular
level. What is the level error on match?
What I have to do? Deny. Okay. I don't
don't add it into the queue. You can say
that it deny. Don't accept it
on mismatch. What you have to do? I said
neutral. Neutral means let the other
filter decide. So you can have multiple
filter like this filter. Filter close.
This is one filter. you can have another
filter. Okay. So it's like from top to
bottom it will run. So neutral means I
don't know let the other filter decide
if there is otherwise ultimately finally
it will get discarded itself. So on
match you can say that either accept or
deny. So I said that okay error one
denied and on match what we should do is
neutral let the other filter decide or
you can also do denied. If this is mash
deny this uh log statement itself in
that case uh the other filter might not
run.
Okay. So this is filter I have added. So
all the log statement apart from error
now get added to the Q and that those
will be passed to non-critical one. Okay
this one when this appender will run.
Now I have writed one critical file
critical this one. So I'm writing one
appender for the critical one. So I am
using file appender. This is the file
name it will create. Now I only want
error to go inside this. Okay. Because
here this is an appender also. So info
will come, debug will come, warn will
come, trace will come, error will come.
So I only want to handle error. I want
to discard all. So I can use threshold
filter. So in threshold filter we can
just put level. So
this level and above would be accepted
and this level below everything would be
rejected. So apart from error warn
info debug trace these all would be
rejected. Only error and above would be
accepted. Above error there is nothing.
So only error would be allowed here in
this
appender.
Okay. And this is my logger. I have
associated both a sync and file
critical. So you can with this logger we
can do anything info log dot error. So
what would happen? So when you do log
info all the appenders will run a sync
also this also. So now let's say first
async will run. What would happen? Okay.
Uh level filter is it uh error? No, it's
an info. So nothing will happen. It will
append into the Q. So currently I'm not
writing it. So by default Q size would
be 256. It would be append worker thread
pick it up and pass it to non-critical.
Non-critical it will append it to a
file. Then the same info would goes to
the file critical. Here what I am doing
is having a filter. I am only accepting
error and above. So info would be
rejected here. Okay. So it will goes
into only non-critical. Similarly when
error comes it will goes to a sync and
file critical both a sync when it goes
it will check okay level is error. Yes
it we will deny it. Okay and uh it will
deny it then we have file critical file
critical what would happen threshold is
error and above. So error yes it is an
error. So it would be accepted and put
into this.
So you got it. So we can have a mix
match of sync
and a sync behavior and we can make use
of filter just to filter out things.
Got it? This is very important right
because we can't have everything a sync.
We can't have everything sync. So there
is always a mismatch always.
Okay.
So now we have covered major logging
part. So some good to know before we
jump to distributed logging and
structured logging very important part
one thing is log format log pattern I
told you right we have something called
encoder okay we have encoder they decide
the format in what in what format
ultimately output would be shown it
would be shown either console or file or
what this is just an place where the log
will go but in what format it will go
that would be decided by our encoder So
like here this it is console. So on
console this is the way it will go date
level
then your logger name message.
Okay. So if you open this pattern layout
on Java. Okay. So we are using pattern
right. So if you open pattern layout on
Java this is a logback framework class.
You will see so many
default which we can use. So here you
might be thinking right how would I know
what to use what is D means what is
level means what is logger means. So
here in this class you would see that D
it is calling this date converter.
Similarly level it is calling level
converter. So if you open this class
level converter you will see what it is
doing is from the event log event it is
take out get level. Okay. So all this
thing we can use as a placeholder in our
pattern. very simple.
Okay. So just open this class. It's
there are so many so it's not possible
to remember it. Whenever you find a use
case that okay this value I need to use
open this class see if it is present and
that placeholder you can use it here.
And if you want to go into the
implementation part what it will do just
go open the class and see what it is
doing it.
Okay. So this is how generally log
format log pattern works.
Then we have something called
placeholder in log statement itself. So
till now what we are doing is log.info
and it is printing it. There might be a
many case where we have to append
something like placeholder
like here what I'm doing is like this
log.info
user who is the user shange
created with ID. What is the id this? So
I am appending it. So this is not
recommended in logging framework.
Okay. Never do string concatenation.
Why? See every log statement has level
info log.info. So you don't know whether
your logger will accept this statement
or not because see your logger has let's
say level one. So it definitely it will
not accept it. But since you are doing a
screen uh string concatenation
no matter whether your log statement get
accepted or not this will get build up.
Okay. So
it's always better or recommended to use
like this way log.info user and then
give a placeholder created with id
placeholder and after that you can give
like so this will go here this will go
here.
Now this placeholder would only be
filled up when your log statement is
accepted. Okay. So you don't unnecessary
has to create the string even though it
is getting rejected. Okay. So you will
save some CPU cycle in a heavy traffic
taking API each CPU cycle matters.
Okay. And in case of exception so let's
say log error payment failed for user
one placeholder. So this shriash will go
over here and then comma exception. So
exception would always be last. Don't
put e comma like shriash. No. So
whenever any exception happens if you
put it at last stack trace would get
also printed.
Okay. So always remember is that if you
have to add exception into log dot error
it would always be last. After all your
placeholders got completed, put it at
the last.
So these are small things. Now let's see
very critical
structured logging
and PII safe logging.
By this time one thing might have come
to our mind that formatting using
pattern is not machine friendly at all.
Why? See now I am doing log.info info
here. Okay. And this is the pattern
which I am using. So how it is showing
it in the console. So this is a console
appender. So it would be like date
then level
then logger name then I'm using hyphen
and then the message.
So here if you see in future if I want I
can change it to like put a pipe here.
Something I can do. So log aggregation
tools have to parse this plain text. So
this plain text they have to parse.
Let's say many time what happen is log
aggregation tools. They are listening to
our logs and you are putting into file
and you told them that hey
listen to this output file to
for the your log aggregation. Now log
aggregation is what they will do is they
will see that okay how many log with
level info what so they will do some
aggregation on top of it right so this
is a plain text so definitely they have
to do some parsing to find out what is
the logger name what is the thread name
what is the date what is the level what
is the message okay so they have to do
parsing to find out all this thing
before they start doing aggregation
and this parsing is not a
straightforward and not 100% correct.
Why? Because they have to rely on
rejects. Okay, if a space comes that
first one is date or this is thing
because this is free form of we are
writing right in the pattern. That's
what I told you currently today I'm
using hyphen. What if tomorrow I change
in some logging or in some logger I am
using pipe. We can have multiple logger
right multiple logger multiple appender.
Each appender can have different encoder
pattern. So for one and appender I am
using this encoding pattern for another
I am using this. So one rejects will not
work for sure and because of that
aggregation tool find it difficult to
parse the pattern
logs which are in plain text.
Okay. And also you can see that in some
logs we can see date like this. Some we
can see that with seconds and also it's
become difficult. It's not easy to
extract useful information from message
also. So here I have you see that I put
very useful information payment ID 1 2
3.
This is critical information which log
aggregation tool might use because in
the log aggregation tool you might have
like hey fetch me a payment ID with 1 2
3 or something
but with this they won't be able to do
anything
because how would they know that in this
message you have something important
which I need to aggregate they won't be
able to aggregate it at all
so it would be better if you can filter
based on payment ID but since it's in
plain text aggregation tool might not be
able to search it and that's where
structured logging JSON comes into the
picture because JSON is something you
can say that it's a friendly
for any machine or generally we are
saying log aggregation
tool so these are nothing but a machines
you can say that which looks for your
output file and if it is in JSON that is
like that the best thing they can get
it's very easy for them to aggregate
but before I proceed further like how
you can do the structured logging please
note it does not mean everything we need
to use JSON when to use JSON only for
those data for which we later might have
to do query filter or some aggregation
that's all for example later you have to
do a search for payment ID ID then it's
better that in the JSON form we can put
it so that on this field it log
aggregation tool put a some index let's
say so they can easily do payment ID
okay for 1 2 3 you got this many events
happened
so whenever you have to do query or
filter or something go for JSON
otherwise
go for plain text so it's always a mix
match again it's not always JSON not
fully 100 plain text it's always a mix
match
Okay,
one thing is incorrect way don't do this
in production that let's say you are
trying to make the pattern itself like
in a JSON. Hey time D level this message
then placeholder
this might work but the thing is that
generally we have so many fields let's
say what about 50 fields you have to do
you have to put into a JSON for log
aggregation okay and it's possible 50 is
very less there are more so generally
it's better not to have it because you
have to keep on extending it and there
is a chance of error also so high chance
of mistake so we have a very best
practice for it yes l use log stash
encoder so I'm telling you for log back
framework persceptive
use log stash encoder so before what
happen is you have a log info we will
convert it to an event then it goes for
pattern formatting then it goes to
appender and then output now here with
the log stash encoder what it will do
log info convert it to a log event this
log event is now converted to
your JSON encoder so it will convert it
to a JSON form
okay now this JSON form goes to a JSON
decorator this is optional this is you
can say that post-processing so there
are many post-processing like you can do
uh pretty print you like you can make
pretty JSON okay And even like in the
JSON if you have to hide few things.
Okay, you can do that. So this you can
say that it's kind of post-processing
before it pass through to the appender
to write it. Okay, so log stash encoder
has this two things. Okay, it convert
the log event to JSON and then we also
have JSON decorator which is optional
which can do postprocessing on this JSON
before it passed to appender.
So for that we need to add a dependency
in pom.xml. So this is the dependency
you need to add. Use any stable version.
Okay. Uh log stash logback encoder is
something which we need to add. And this
is the appender. Now I'm adding. See
this how simple it is. Appender name is
JSON console. You can give any name. Why
I give JSON console? Because I am using
a console appender and encoder I am
using JSON one. So that's why JSON. You
can give any name.
So this is my output. Still I am
printing on output. But what format my
encoder is which I am using is like log/
encoder. Now
okay and here if you see I am not using
any pattern. Now I am using encoder.
This will decide like how to convert it
to a JSON.
So this class accept log event and fetch
the details from the log event like
logger name, thread name etc.
Okay. So now question might have come to
you that hey Shange
what all fields
this will fetch log/enccoder will fetch.
So if you open this class log field
names do java. So you will see that it
has this many field at the rate time
stamp at the rate version message thread
name logger name level stack trace uh
caller class name caller method name
caller file name caller line number
everything. So these are some of the you
can say that fields which are already
present which it tried to fetch from the
log event.
Okay. So this is already present. So
open this class and see that what all
presents here. Okay. So for thread name
it will do log event dot get thread
name. Okay. Uh log event dot what is the
logger name? What is the level name? So
it will try to fetch everything from
this log event itself.
Okay. And then we can easily configure
our logger. So this is my logger. My
logger name level is info. Additivity
false. I don't want to propagate upward.
Appender which I am referring is JSON
console. So this one I am associating my
logger.
So now if you see the output if you do
log info something I'm just doing the
log.info. So see the output now on the
console. So here I am using console
appender right. So on console only come
but now in this form log form JSON form.
So at the time stem these all fields are
present at the time stamp. So this time
version message log info and the payment
ID 1 2 3 whatever login name thread name
level level level value. So
all these fields are present which it
will try to fetch it from your log event
and it will show like this.
Now definitely question would come to
you that hey what about some dynamic
fields I want to add like okay these are
some of the information which are
present in my log statement it is able
to fetch it is able to fetch the message
okay so it able to fetch message logger
name thread name date everything it's
okay what is the level it's in the JSON
form but the real power of structured
JSON is that dynamic field which I
should be able to add into the JSON so
that my aggregation tool can also use
this those new field because these are
very limited okay there might be many
field let's say here in the message I
have payment ID payment ID 1 2 3 so
let's say what if in JSON it would be
better if I have let's say something
payment ID and 1 2 3 so that log
aggregation tool might be able to
aggregate based on the payment ID field
also like how many different unique
payment ID I got in a day something we
can do query out of it
so that's where MDC comes into the
picture map diagnostic context please
note I will not go MDC here now I will
go into the next part last part of
distributed logging where I would be
cover distributed logging part also
because MDC also plays critical role in
the distributed logging
Okay, but for now I'm just saying just
for now how dynamic
value we can append into the JSON. So
here we have something like MDC.put. So
it's a static method MDC.put.
Whatever the field you want to add and
whatever the value you want to add
dynamically in your code you can have
make sure that you are doing it before
the log
wherever log.info info
before that you have to put it because
when you create a log event
the log event will fetch this value from
this MDC
because if you do after this
means you you have already done all this
thing log.info info means you have
already done you have already convert to
log event from log event you have
already convert to JSON this JSON is
already passed to the appender appender
already write it and after that you are
doing mdcput
it will not be used so you have to
before it so that it will goes to this
event log event and which can pass it to
ultimate to JSON
so here by default the our log log stash
encoder has access to MDC.
Okay. So if you don't want you can
always make it false. Include MDC you
can false it. Uh this encoder
log/enccoder you can make it false so
that it will not try to access your MDC.
Whatever the data is present in your MDC
it will not try to access it. But by
default it is true. And when it is true,
when the JSON encoder converts your log
event to JSON, apart from log event, it
will also read your MDC
and it will take out all the keys value
and put it into the JSON form. And your
JSON would be like timestamp, version,
payment, your whatever the logger
message like payment is successful,
logger name, thread name, whatever the
previously we have seen. Now all the
fields which are present into MDC that
will also come payment ID 1 2 3 that's
the power of structured logging.
Okay.
So MDC is very important topic and can
be used with distributed logging. So we
will cover in depth in the next part
most probably the last part of the
distributed logging.
So now we know how to generate a
structured logging. Now very important
is we should never log P III data
personally identifiable information.
Very important.
Okay. So one golden rule is if you don't
know if particular data is PII or not
never log it because if you log it and
it turned out to be a PI data it's a
compliance issue. Okay. So generally
government bodies then charge fine.
So what is considered as PI data? So any
information through which we can
identify a specific person directly or
indirectly like phone number, address,
Aadhaar card, pen card, email, OTP,
password these are all covered uh as PII
data because we they can be used to
identify one specific person directly or
indirectly and there are so many things.
So whatever information you are trying
to log if you're not sure whether this
could be a PI data or not check it
search online there I think there is a
list in the PII there is some
documentation which has all the
information which can be considered as
PII. So see whatever you are trying to
log consider as PI or not.
But with the structured logging we have
a way to save it. So that by mistake if
it we are putting it we can save it and
like how we do is so we know that we
have a log info log convert to log event
it goes to JSON encoder convert it to a
JSON. I told you about JSON decorator
which is like a postprocessing
here we can make use of it.
So we can make use of JSON decorator.
Okay. And it's like a postprocessing
which we can use for just JSON pretty.
Currently JSON is like in very form of
like plain text right like this. So if
have like a proper JSON nested and all
it's like a pretty form you can do that
also or you can also use it to mask
sensitive fields how so here if you see
I am creating an appender JSON console
so my appender is
write the log statement to console but
what encoder I am using to format my is
like log/ encoder so ultimately I would
be putting into the JSON form
Now I am using a decorator JSON
generator decorator. Okay. And the class
which I'm using is masking JSON
generator decorator. So there are
multiple classes which we can use for
pretty. For pretty JSON pretty there
could be different class which we can
use within this decorator.
But for masking we have this masking
JSON generator decorator. Here we can
tell the default mask. So you can say
it's like a placeholder which will which
fe will be used for masking. So default
mask I want like a star star star like
this. What are the field to mask? So
password token credit card. So I have
just put this path. So these are path is
nothing but a field. So whatever the
JSON file which you have or you can say
that the JSON log log in the JSON form
if in that log any fields are this those
would be changed to star star star like
this no matter if they are within a
nested object or not okay if across this
JSON if any of this field is present
they will get masked with this
placeholder.
Okay. So, decorator close and this one.
So, now here if you see
in / payments I have MDC. So,
dynamically I'm just so payment ID and
for testing purpose I'm putting hey
password is this is my password. So you
we know that from MDC it will read it
and convert add it to JSON and this is
my decorator error I'm looking for
password also that it should mask it. So
here if you see
payment ID added properly but password
is changed to star star star instead of
my password.
Okay.
So in the next part we will see MDC very
important and finally the distributed
logging because till now whatever we are
doing it is applicable like we can do in
a single application too. Now what
happen when we have more than one
service more than one application and
how MDC helps there also so we'll say
that. So any doubt let me know we can
discuss further. Bye.